All right. Thank you, Brittany, yeah, so as Brittany said
I'm a colleague of Brittany's just down the hall, I run the Developer Experience Design Lab where
we run studies of developers and try to build new programming tools.
So imagine that you're debugging an input issue, so you're looking at some snake game,
you're trying to get the snake to move,
you're you're entering the up down left right keys,
but it doesn't seem to be working just right. So what do you do?
One thing you might try is just to add some break points,
so try to find the input handlers for all these - these keyboard events and
see what happens when they're invoked. But this isn't the only thing you might do.
A different way to try to debug this is to just be - to start at the end,
to start at the output, go to find the statement
that is generating the output and then try to follow the the data flow backwards
to see, sort of, at what point the data flow doesn't look quite right.
And there's all sorts of other approaches you might imagine and lots of variations
on these approaches. But often in practice
this ends up being Stack Overflow of course. But how do you choose the right approach?
What I want to talk to you today about is a way that you can try to grow your toolbox in a way
that is more deliberate, right, than accidental. And I'd like to try to give you a tool that tries
to rescue yourself from your own worst self. And I want to talk to you about a version of
you that is doing interesting work and solving difficult problems,
whose colleagues come to them because they just have a different way of looking at things.
And the secret sauce I'm going to try to give you today is this idea of a programming strategy.
A programming strategy is just a procedure for accomplishing a programming task.
I mean,
it offers this language for shaping how software engineering effort happens.
Most of - most of programming is all about solving problems,
so you want to fix some issue, and the way you do that is,
you know, first you find a defect and then you try
to trace the output backwards to find the defect and to trace the output backwards you need to
find where the output is first generated. So whenever you're going through one of
these - these problems you always have these nested problems that you're trying to solve.
And psychologists have long looked at how humans solve problems
and a big part of this is just trial and error. So problem solving is often like a maze where
humans are just trying to choose which path to follow
and people end up backtracking a lot when choices just don't work out as as you expect.
So programming strategy just gives you a way to try to navigate this - this maze more effectively.
And there's evidence that over time experienced developers learn how to use strategies
that help them to work more effectively. So how can you learn another developer's strategy?
So you may just ask somebody to write it down and try to follow it.
But we found that this isn't quite as easy as it seems.
So as a developer you have a tendency to just read the whole strategy all at once rather than
going through it all step by step and then as you try to use it you
can lose track of where you are in that strategy and, you know, forget, like what you're trying to
do next and have to start over from the beginning. Or you might try to follow it for a while, get
confused, and then just go back to doing whatever was the approach you'd otherwise be doing before.
And this makes sense. Whenever you're solving a problem
there's a lot of what's called cognitive load, there's a lot of things you're trying to pay
attention to. I mean,
it's hard to pay attention both to the problem and learning something new at the same time.
So habit is really strong and it ends up being very hard to overcome.
So to help address this we invented a way to try to learn a strategy.
We built what we call a strategy tracker. And the idea is it lets you go step by
step through the strategy and just helps you keep track of where you are in the strategy
and just take notes as you're working.
And we even invented this this more formal notation for describing these strategies
which then led us built an interpreter that helps the
strategy tracker keep track of the control flow to determine what step to show the developer next.
And we can even do things like help the developer try to remember what to do later
by having them write things down which we just assign into a variable
and then we can sort of reference that variable later in the strategy
when the developer needs to go back to to something later in the strategy.
So then using this notation, if you want to write a detailed
strategy that explains how to debug by doing backward data flow search,
you can do that in our notation.
So we found that with all of this
we were able to successfully enable a developer to switch strategies
and for this defect, switching to a backwards search
helps them to work better. And in fact it helped them to
make more progress than they would have otherwise been able to make
because that strategy was a better fit for the problem that they were trying to solve.
But where do you find strategies? Can we just go off and ask experienced
developers to start writing them? So it's possible that these
strategies might be what's called tacit - that developers just learn the new strategy
but never even realize that they're following it, and because it's tacit it isn't something that
they could try to explicitly write down and explain.
So are they tacit? So again we try to find out,
and we just asked developers to write down some strategies for us.
And we found that they largely could. We found that, you know,
developers are able to write all sorts of strategies for all sorts of problems.
But it's often hard to write good strategies because it's
often hard to generalize the strategy, to go through the process of testing it,
to make sure it works on all the different variants of the the problem that you might have,
and to try to take the perspective of a strategy user that might not
have exactly the expertise that you have and be able to explain things at the right level
of detail that somebody else could could follow. But we found that developers for these good
strategies can try to use them to - to solve a programming problem,
they just often have the same sorts of challenges that the people have in writing them,
where, you know, there might be missing steps, there might be ambiguity,
it might not tell you how to use all these - these tools.
So the main takeaway of both of these findings is that in order to build this
process - to successfully to share strategies, it's really important to have a feedback process.
Or you want somebody to first try to write it and then you want a revision
process for people using it to give comments and for the person writing it to make it better
so that over time you can address all these these issues in - in strategies.
A few more cautionary notes about choosing strategies.
As you might imagine,
the type of code that you're looking at has a big impact on the strategy you might choose.
So if you're working in code that interacts closely with the library,
you're over three times more likely to go find some docs and kind of less likely to build a
diagram to try to understand what's going on which which all makes sense.
But how you're feeling can also have a really profound impact
on how you decide to approach a problem. So if you're feeling stressed or nervous
you're twice as likely to add print statements, and over five times less likely to try to spend
the time to read all the code nearby, which just might be too complicated.
If you're feeling sad or depressed, you're over 10 times less likely to
try to experiment by just editing the code which is a lot of speculative hoping that, you know,
you randomly get lucky and get what you want. And if you're feeling very excited
and enthusiastic you're over twice as likely to ask for help from a colleague.
So how can you be proud of the way you work and work in a way that is more
deliberate rather than accidental? One key takeaway is that there's
always - almost always a different strategy that you might use to try to tackle a problem.
Just being aware of this - explicitly considering a strategy that might work
the best for your situation in this moment - is an example of what's called metacognition.
Some studies have also demonstrated that that self-regulation - the process of monitoring
your progress and your use of time - are also associated with greater
problem solving success.
You can also just find better strategies. So there's there's resources out there
today that try to document some of the ways that you can solve problems
and just knowing more of these - these strategies can help you to be more effective.
But you can also try to, like, be more of an active participant,
to share your own strategies and help curate strategies that work for your own organization.
So we've been building this tool called How to Dev that can act
as a repository for - for strategies like this. And finally it's important to think about how your
own affect is approaching your - your approach. Like, taking a minute to de-stress or help
yourself feel better can really have an impact on how you solve problems.
If you really want to learn more about strategies we're going to be running these - these
programming strategies mentoring sessions, so reach out to us for that.
So with that I'm here for any questions anybody might have.
Fantastic, super, thank you so much. First an enlightening talk on programming
strategies that I wish I had heard a really long time ago
or at least that I think that - the connections in particular, right, are interesting, between,
like, our our mental state, our being, and how we do things in ways that we can
think about navigating that as well it's a really interesting connections here.
I do have one question that I see, and again, audience, please feel
free to bring the questions onto Slack. Rebecca wants to know, do you know that
they really follow a particular strategy that they write down or is it more nuanced?
Thinking about the fact that in different contexts experts might vary their strategy
slightly depending on the task or - or the context or domain.
Any thoughts on that? Yeah, I think - a great question.
I mean, a lot of these strategies have a lot of nuance and complexity.
So when we asked somebody to write it down, it - it's probably, like, you know, a high-level sketch
of how they see themselves as solving this problem
and might not have every sort of complication or variant of - of the problem,
so I think definitely trying to to grow these strategies over time through feedback,
to flush out more of these - these corner cases, is definitely way to go,
since you're probably not going to write the perfect strategy the first time.